<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | JonLz's Coding Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://JonLz.github.com/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://JonLz.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-11T18:46:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://JonLz.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lots to catch up on]]></title>
    <link href="http://JonLz.github.com/blog/2012/10/16/lots-to-catch-up-on/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T14:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://JonLz.github.com/blog/2012/10/16/lots-to-catch-up-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, I'm about 2 months behind now on starting this blog but better late than never, right? I began my foray about 2 months ago and discovered the Ruby language and more importantly, the fantastic Ruby community.  I sort of stumbled into ruby because I really wanted to learn a web framework and found out about ruby on rails.  I had no idea what ruby was and thought the code in rails was pretty wickedly awesome - then I discovered it was just built on top of ruby, mindblowing.  Since then, I took a step back and dived pretty deep into ruby in order to become proficient in it.  I'm at an okay point with it now and will be venturing back into rails which should hopefully be a little easier now.  I still &lt;3 ruby though.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I'm going to spend a few posts talking about specific ruby idioms and programs I've worked on just to flesh some thoughts out, and then it's onward to rails and other html/css stuff that is also necessary to learn.</p>

<p>My goal with this blog is to stay accountable to my progress through coding and becoming a better developer.
It's also awesome to share things I learn with people as I've found in my short time in the coding community
that everyone is super willing to help and there's so many free resources out there.  Thanks to anyone out there reading this who contributes to open source / online education!</p>

<p>Also apparently I have a hard time posting code snippets using octopress because I can't figure out how to get python dependencies enabled.. or so I've been reading.  There are windows users with certain IDEs (I guess I'm one of them, yay) where Octopress can't run the rubypython gem and load python correctly to parse the code snippet into html.  Bleck, in the meanwhile my code snippets will just be unhighlighted and unnamed.  Some day when I join the dark (light?) side and get a mac to program on maybe this will all change.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>def rubyruby&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre>&lt;code>puts codeblock
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p>end</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
